Guide to the Italian Castle Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- MISCELLANY, 47 manuscript and 8 printed documents, comprising 727
  - (Altieri, Cardinal Paluzzo). A letter of complaint by the ambassadors of France, Spain, Germany, and Venice against the Cardinal Altieri who did not grant them an audience with Pope Clement X. Undated, unsigned. 1674-1675. 9 pages, numbered ff. 266-270. (Box 83, Folder 34)
  - Ristretto della Congragatione tenuta Domenica 7 Novembre 1683. Comments on the edict against the immodesty of ladies' dresses. 4 pages, numbered ff. 272-273. (Box 83, Folder 35)
  - Lollus, Paul, S.Th.D. Disceptatio Theologica et Canonica circa acceptionem, recusationem aut renunciationem Cardinalatus. A dissertation on Canon law on acceptance and refusal of the Cardinalship. In Latin. Undated, unsigned. 10 pages, numbered ff. 274-278. 1681, according to a heading added later. (Box 83, Folder 36)
  - Alibert, Count Giacomo d'. All'Illustrissimi... Prelati, e Deputati dell'Archiconfraternita de S. Girolamo della Carrita. A letter and statement, unsigned and undated, on the construction of a new theater by the architects Carlo Fontana and Giovanni Antonio de Rossi. Circa 1693. This new Theatro di Tordinona was opened on Jan. 25, 1696. Count Alibert was the originator of the first public musical theater in Rome. 7 pages, numbered ff. 280-285. (Box 83, Folder 37)
  - Padrone, Ferdinando. Alla Sagra Congregatione Deputata... Printed leaflet, with detailed costs, of an aquaduct to Civita Vecchia. Rome, nella stamperia della Rev. Cam. Apost., 1695. 8 leaves, numbered ff. 286-293. (Box 83, Folder 38)
  - Ristretto e dimonstratione degl'utili, e commodi, che sono per resultarne dalla Condotta dell'Aqua... A printed discourse on the advantages of the aquaduct in Civita Vecchia, with detailed specifications, which was being built by Ferdinando Padrone. Rome, per Antoni de Rossi, 1703. 8 pages, numbered ff. 294-297. (Box 83, Folder 39)
  - Utrumque edictum Mediolanense procul dubio subiacet dispositioni Bullae Caenae Domini... A treatise in Latin, apparently a draft concerning a Milan edict referring to a Papal Bull (by Innocent XII?) with historic references to controversies between the Lombardic states and the Court of Rome. Also with passages in Italian. Undated and unsigned. 10 pages, numbered ff. 298-303. (Box 83, Folder 40)
  - Relazione dell'arrivo fatto in Praga da Carlo terzo Re della Spagna. A detailed description of the ceremonies and festivities at the visit to Prague of Charles III, King of Spain. Charles, son of Leopold I, and later Charles VI as Holy Roman Emperor, was acknowledged King of Spain as Charles III in 1703 against Philip V. Dated Sept. 26, unsigned. The visit to Prague must have taken place between 1703 and 1711. 5 pages, numbered ff. 304-306. (Box 83, Folder 41)
  - (Louvain, University of). Pareri dell'Universita di Lovanio... The opinion of the doctors of the University of Louvain in the case of William of Orange, allied with Austria, against James II of England who had converted to Roman Catholicism and whom the Prince of Orange succeeded in 1689 as William III of England. The political situation was deeply involved in the controversies of Jansenism and the "case of conscience." Undated, unsigned (before 1689). 15 pages, numbered ff. 308-316. (Box 83, Folder 42)
  - Sincerissimo ma altretanto detestabile fatto sotte la parola di fede successo alle Truppe Allemanne... An account of the evacuation of German troops from Ficcarolo on the Po River through the intervention of the Papal Legate in Ferrara, Cardinal Fulvio Astalli. Containing copy of the letter by Astalli, dated June 20, 1704, and the account of the return of the French to the city despite contrary promises to the Germans. 6 pages, numbered ff. 317-319. (Box 83, Folder 43)
  - Ceremoniale per Sua Maesta...il trattamento dei li Cardinali. Instructions for the ceremonial to be observed at the visit of Maria Casimira, widow of John Sobieski, King of Poland, who retired to Rome in 1698, with references to Christina, Queen of Sweeden. At the end, a copy of a letter in Latin to the Queen of Poland by Pope Innocent XII, dated Dec. 1, 1698. 5 pages, numbered ff. 320-322. (Box 83, Folder 44)
  - Vigili, Fabio, Bishop of Spoleto. Imperatori. Super actis in Conventu Spirensi. Copy of a letter by the Bishop of Spoleto to Emperor Charles V, concerning the Imperial Diet at Speyer of June, 1544. In Latin. Dated Rome, August 24, 1544. Some holes and stains, effecting a few words. Title and 17 pages, numbered ff. 323-332. (Box 83, Folder 45)
  - Corsini, Ottavio, Archbishop of Tarsos. Copy of a letter by Corsini, Pope Gregory XV's Nuncio to France, written to Louis XIII, exhorting him to continue to fight against the Hueguenots. Dated April 15, 1622. 14 pages, numbered ff. 335-341. (Box 83, Folder 46)
  - Ragguaglio del'Viaggio datto da N.S. Papa Innocentio XII... Report of a trip made by Pope Innocent XII in April of 1697, with description of the churches and palaces visited, including the works of art, the receptions, the gifts received, and gifts given to the Viceroy of Naples. 22 pages folio and 6 pages 8vo, numbered ff. 349-362. (Box 83, Folder 47)
  - Nota de preparamenti fatti dal Principe Borghese nella Tenuta di Carocceto... Preparations made by Prince Borghese for Pope Innocent XII's visit to Nettuno, including the meals served, the hostelries closed for security reasons, etc. Also, the presents given to the Pope by various persons. Apparently referring to the same papal trip as in the item above (no. 47). 11 pages, numbered ff. 363-368. (Box 83, Folder 48)
  - ...in Relatione del Viaggio fatto dalla...Papa Innocentio XII à Civita Vecchia. Report on the trip to Civita Vecchia by Pope Innocent XII, written by "N.N." With lists of presents given to the Pope by Cardinals, princes, etc. Also a list of presents to the Pope in Castle St. Guido. All referring to the Pope's trip in 1697 (see above two items, nos. 47 & 48). 12 pages, numbered ff. 369-377. (Box 83, Folder 49)
  - Racconto della Legazione del Card. Boncompagni alla Regina de Romani... A detailed description of the reception of the Queen of Romania in Modena by Cardinal Giacomo Boncompagni, archbishop of Bologna, who had been assigned this task by Pope Innocent XII. With enumeration of the attending officials and questions of the ceremonial. Unsigned. (16 January, 1699). 10 pages, numbered ff. 378-382. (Box 83, Folder 50)
  - Aste, Cardinal Marcello d', Archbishop of Ancona. Testamento. Printed testament of the Cardinal Marcello d'Aste who died in Bologna on June 11, 1709. The testament was published and opened by the notary Paolo Novello on June 15, 1709. With large woodcut of the Cardinal's arms on the title. 12 pages, numbered ff. 384-389. Rome, nella stamperia di Gio. Francesco Chracas, 1709. (Box 83, Folder 51)
  - Pallavicini, Cardinal Ranuccio. Schedola Testamentaria. Printed testament by the Cardinal Pallavicini who died June 30, 1712. 3 pages, numbered ff. 390-391. N.p., n.d. (1712). (Box 83, Folder 52)
  - Rospigliosi, Maria Camilla Pallavicini, Duchess of Zagarolo. Testamento... Printed testament, dated May 2, 1707, and published in 1710. 12 leaves, numbered ff. 392-403. N.p., typis de Comitibus, 1710. (Box 83, Folder 53)
  - Charles II, King of Spain. Copia del Testamento che alli 2 Ottobre 1700, e del Codocillo, che alli 5 del medesimo Mese, ed anno hà fatto...Dopo la di cui dispozione mancòdi Vita il primo Novembre susseguente. Printed testament of Charles II of Spain, whose death on Nov. 1, 1700 caused the War of the Spanish Succession. (Box 83, Folder 54)
  - In this will as his 13th point, he names Philip d'Anjou (Philip V) as his heir and successor. It is published herein Galleria di Minerva, Tome IV, Part IV, pp. 65-84, with a title leaf and a full-page engraved portrait of Charles II. Venice, Girolamo Abrizzi, 1700. Title, engraved portrait, and 9 pages, numbered ff. 404-415.
  - Reflessione sopra il Manifesto del Conte di Melgar, Almirante di Castiglia... Reflections on the manifest by the Count of Melgar from Lisbon, Jan. 29, 1704, concerning the testament of Charles II of Spain (see above, no. 54) and the Spanish Succession. (c. 1704, unsigned). 8 pages, numbered ff. 416-419. (Box 83, Folder 55)
- INSTRUTTIONI PER LI NUNTII IN ELVETIA
  Instruttioni per li Nuntii in Elvetia. 23 manuscript documents and 1 printed broadside, comprising 327 pages, numbered ff. 1-189. Folio. Contemporary vellum. Italy, 17th century.
  - Aste, Marcellus de, Archbishop of Athens. Proclomation by Marcello de Aste, Pope Innocent XII's Nuncio in Switzerland, concerning tax regulation. Printed broadside, 4 columns within a frame of typographical ornaments. Large folio, folded. Dated Lucerne, March 17, 1694. (Box 84, Folder 1)
  - Ristretto del Instrutione per Monsignore Nuntio d'Elvetia. Short instructions to the Nuncio in Switzerland, unsigned, undated. Probably for Alessandro Scappi, the successor of Ludovico di Sarego, who was Nuncio from 1613-1621. Gives information of the temporal and spiritual organization of the 8 Catholic cantons of Switzerland, on the bishops, abbots, orders, and monasteries. 11 pages, numbered ff. 1-6. (Box 84, Folder 2)
  - Cinque sono li Vescovi soggetti alla Nunziatura dll'Elvezia... Report of a Nuncio in Switzerland, on the 5 bishoprics, the jurisdiction of the bishops, etc. Undated, unsigned. Probably at the time of Pope Alexander VIII (1689-1691), with mention of Pierre Montenach, Bishop of Lusanne (1688-1707), other personalities and events of Catholic interest in the Swiss cantons. 8 pages, numbered ff. 7-10. (Box 84, Folder 3)
  - Notizie d'alcune particolarita ritratte dal Legature di Monsig. Borromeo che venne a Roma... Notes on the Swiss nunciature from a report of Frederico Bartolomeo, made on a visit to Rome in 1664. Bartolomeo was Nuncio in Switzerland from 1655-1665. 3-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 11-12. (Box 84, Folder 4)
  - Notizie per il nuovo Nuntio ai Suizzieri. Rules for the household of the Swiss Nuncio, his staff, food, furniture, his official duties, his relations to the clergy and to diplomats. Unsigned and undated. Probably around 1665, after Borromeo finished his nunciature. 5-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 13-15. (Box 84, Folder 5)
  - (Relazione della Nunziatura). A detailed report from Switzerland, apparently by a staff member of the Papal Nuncio there, to the Pope. Contains accounts of the government of the Swiss cantons, of the ceremonies of the Nuncio at audiences, the duties and jurisdiction of the Nuncio, and the diplomacy needed in the ticklish situation between the Catholic and Protestant sections of the country. With lists of the monasteries of the various orders in Switzerland. Undated, unsigned. (After 1630, probably under the Papacy of Pope Urban VIII). 54 pages, numbered ff. 19-45. (Box 84, Folder 6)
  - Borghese, Cardinal Scipione. Instruttione à Mons. Sarego, Vescovo d'Adria destinato Nuntio nell'Elvetia da PP. Paolo V. Detailed instructions to Ludovico di Sarego, who was Nuncio in Switzerland 1613-1621. Dated Rome, Sept. 2, 1614 and signed by Cardinal Scipione Borghese, then camerlengo of the Church. 112 pages, numbered ff. 49-104. (Box 84, Folder 7)
  - (Assemblea del Clero, tenuta in Parigi l'anno 1682). A report on the assembly of the French Clergy in Paris, 1682, which, on the order of Louis XIV, decided on the controversies of the Regalia and the Papal power as opposed to worldly power, problems which led to constant tensions between Pope Innocent XI and Louis XIV of France. 28 pages, numbered ff. 107-120. (Box 84, Folder 8)
  - (Innocent XII, Pope). Letter in Latin, naming Marcello d'Aste Archbishop of Athens. Unsigned, undated (Dec., 1692). 2 pages (f. 123). (Box 84, Folder 9)
  - (Baldeschi, Fredericus). Copies of several letters by and concerning Baldeschi, Papal Nuncio in Switzerland 1665-1668, to the Catholic cantons. Undated, unsigned. 8 pages, numbered ff. 125-128. (Box 84, Folder 10)
  - Ristretto delle Facolta de' SS. Nunzii come Prelati famigliari et Assistenti. On certain privilidges granted to the Nuncios. 1 page (f. 129). (Box 84, Folder 11)
  - Informazioni delle cose versenti con Monsig. Vescovo di Losanna, del Card. Colonna. Instructions by Cardinal Colonna to the Bishop of Lusanne. Undated, unsigned. Possibly at the time of Borromeo's nunciature in Switzerland, 1655-1665. 6 pages, numbered ff. 130-132. (Box 84, Folder 12)
  - Instruzione per Mons. Ilustrissimo d'Asti. Specific instructions for Marcello d'Aste, who was Nuncio in Switzerland from 1692-1695, referring to various abbeys, to ceremonies, to trouble spots in certain counties, etc. Undated, unsigned. Probably written early in his nunciature. Title page and 14 pages, numbered ff. 135-142. Large folio, folded. (Box 84, Folder 13)
  - (Informationi dalla Secretario di Stato). Information of Switzerland which the Nuncios are urged to study before departing from Rome. This information seems to be based on the experience of Giacomo Cantelmi who had been Papal Nuncio from 1685 to 1687 and had been made cardinal in 1690. Probably directed to Marcello d'Aste who started his Nunciature in Lucerne in 1692. Unsigned, undated. 6-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 143-146. Large folio, folded. (Box 84, Folder 14)
  - Alcuni informationi circa la Nuntiatura e Citta di Lucerna. Some notes concerning the house occupied by the Papal Nuncio in Lucerne, the senate of the city, the bishoprics under the Nuncio's jurisdiction, etc. Undated, unsigned. Circa 1667. 2-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 147-148. (Box 84, Folder 15)
  - Notizie per il nuovo Nunzio. Notes for a new Nuncio in Switzerland, what he should do on his arrival in Lucerne, how much money he should carry with him, etc. 1 page (f. 149). Undated, unsigned. (Box 84, Folder 16)
  - Informatione per Mons. Nunzio di Lucerna. More notes of advice for a new Nuncio coming to Switzerland, about his staff, expenses, questions of diplomatic ceremony, his relationship withthe citizens and government of Lucerne, etc. Undated, unsigned. The same secretary (Giov. Antonio Rusconi) is recommended as in No. 15. The date is probably around 1668, and the instructions might be for the successor of Fridericus Baldeschi who left Lucerne in 1668. 4 pages, numbered ff. 150-151. (Box 84, Folder 17)
  - Nota di quello costano a Mons. Illustrissimo Nuntio la Lettiga con suoi finimenti, e due muli, quali adesso saranno di anni otto. An account of the cost of the carriage and mules for the Nuncio in Switzerland, apparently taken from the costs incurred by Giacomo Cantelmo and his successor, given as useful information to the new Nuncio, Marcello d'Aste. Undated, unsigned. Circa 1692. 1 page (f. 153). (Box 84, Folder 18)
  - Paramenti per Mons. Illustrissimo Nuntio... Lists on the Church requisites and on the staff needed by the Nuncio in Switzerland. Undated, unsigned. 2 pages (f. 154). (Box 84, Folder 19)
  - A Mons. Nunzio inviato alle Hti. Suizzeri, Grigioni, e Loro Sudditi e Confederati possono darsi le seguenti notitie. Information for the new Nuncio on the Swiss people, of whom it is said are well-educated, that they don't like innovations or ostentatious bahavior; on money needed. Giacomo Cantelmo is mentioned who was Nuncio in Switzerland from 1685-1687. Undated, unsigned. 4 pages, numbered ff. 157-158. Large folio, folded. (Box 84, Folder 20)
  - (Aste, Marcello d'). Quando Mons. Illustrissimo d'Asti non habbia sin'hora scritto alli Cantoni Cattolici... An urgent advice to Marcello d'Aste, who went as Nuncio to Switzerland in 1692 to write two letters to the Catholic cantons. Also other briefings on Switzerland and on the Nuncio's duties there. Undated, unsigned (c. 1692). 6-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 159-162. Stained. (Box 84, Folder 21)
  - Che debba fare il Nunzio per dar sodisfazione in cose temporali nella Nunziatura de Suizeri. Information on the character and government of the Swiss people, how to treat them, and how to behave in negotiations with them in order to win their confidence. Undated, unsigned. 8-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 163-167. (Box 84, Folder 22)
  - (Una breve relatione della Nuntiatura de Suizzari). Information on the political situation in Switzerland, particularly in the Veltlin, with advice to the Nuncio, the moneys and credentials he has to bring, etc. Undated and unsigned. 9 pages, numbered ff. 169-173. Possibly directed to Alessandro Scappi, who was Nuncio in Switzerland from 1621 to 1628. (Box 84, Folder 23)
  - Instruzione all'...Duca di Fiano, Destinato della Santita di...Papa Gregorio XV a pigliar il deposito a Nome di S. Santita e della Sede Apostolica delli Forti della Valltellina. Instructions to Orazio Ludovisi, the Duke of Fiano, brother of Pope Gregory XV, when he was sent with the Papal troops to Veltlin in 1623. Dated Rome, April 5 (1623). 29-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 175-189. (Box 84, Folder 24)
- RELATIONI DI CONCLAVI
  Relationi di Conclavi. 18 manuscript documents, comprising 1063 pages, numbered ff. 1-536. 4to. Contemporary vellum. Italy (Rome), 17th century.
  - Conclava delle Sede Vacante di Papa Leone Xmo nel quale fu creato Papa Adriano VI. Account of the election of Pope Adrian VI in 1521, with a list of the Cardianls at the Conclave. 21 pages, numbered ff. 1-11. (Box 85, Folder 1)
  - Conclave della Sede Vacante di Papa Adreano VI nel qual fu creato Papa Clemente VII. Account of the election of Pope Clement VII in 1523. 20 pages, numbered ff. 12-21. (Box 85, Folder 2)
  - Questa elettione piace a molti... An historical survey of the papacies of the two Medicean Popes Leo X and Clement VII, made upon the election of Pope Paul III in 1533. 61 pages, numbered ff. 22-52. (Box 85, Folder 3)
  - Conclave della sede vacante di Papa Clemente VII ne qual fu creato Papa Paolo Terzo. Account of the election of Pope Paul III in 1533. 21 pages, numbered ff. 53-63. (Box 85, Folder 4)
  - Conclave della Sede Vacante di Papa Paolo Terzo nel quale fu creato Papa Giulio Terzo. Account of the election of Pope Julius III in 1534. 66 pages, numbered ff. 64-96. (Box 85, Folder 5)
  - Conclave delle Sede Vacante di Papa Giulio Terzo nel quale fu creato Papa Marcello Secondo. Account of the election of Pope Marcellus II in 1555. 28 pages, numbered ff. 97-110. (Box 85, Folder 6)
  - Conclave delle Sede Vacante di Papa Marcello Secondo nel quale fu creato Papa Paolo IV. An account of the election of Pope Paul IV in 1555; with a list of Cardinals at the conclave. 31 pages, numbered ff. 111-126. (Box 85, Folder 7)
  - Conclave delle Sede Vacante di Papa Paolo IV nel quale fu creato Papa Pio Quarto. An account of the election of Pope Pius IV in 1559. 24 pages, numbered ff. 127-138. (Box 85, Folder 8)
  - Conclave della Sede Vacante di Papa Pio IV nel quale fu creato Papa Pio Quinto. Account of the election of Pope Pius V in 1566. 73 pages, numbered ff. 139- 175. (Box 85, Folder 9)
  - Conclave delle Sede Vacante di Papa Pio V nel quale fu creato Papa Gregorio XIII. Account of the election of Pope Gregory XIII in 1572, with a list of Cardinals at the Conclave. 19 pages, numbered ff. 176-185. (Box 85, Folder 10)
  - Conclave della Sede Vacante di Papa Gregorio XIII nel quale fu creato Papa Sisto Quinto. Account of the election of Pope Sixtus V in 1585; with a list of the Cardinals at the Conclave. 32 pages, numbered ff. 186-201. (Box 85, Folder 11)
  - Conclave della Sede Vacante di Papa Sisto Quinto nel quale fu creato Papa Urbano Settimo. Account of the election of Pope Urban VII in 1590; with a list of Cardinals at the Conclave. 36 pages, numbered ff. 202-219. (Box 85, Folder 12)
  - Conclave della Sede Vacante di Papa Urbano Settimo nel quale fu creato Papa Gregorio Decimo Quarto. Account of the election of Pope Gregory XIV in 1590; with a list of the Cardinals present at the Conclave. 191 pages, numbered ff. 220-313. (Box 85, Folder 13)
  - Conclave della Sede Vacante di Papa Gregorio XIV nel quale fu creato Papa Innocento IX. Account of the election of Pope Innocent IX; with a list of Cardinals present at the Conclave. 78 pages, numbered ff. 314-352. (Box 85, Folder 14)
  - Conclave della Sedia Vacante di Papa Innocento IX nel quale fu creato Papa Clemente VIII. Account of the election of Pope Clement VIII in 1592; with a list of Cardinals at the Conclave. 91 pages, numbered ff. 353-398. (Box 85, Folder 15)
  - Conclave di Gregorio Decimo Quinto. Account of the election of Pope Gregory XV in 1621; with a list of Cardinals at the Conclave. 39 pages, numbered ff. 400-419. (Box 85, Folder 16)
  - Conclave del anno MDCXXXIII (sic) nel quale fu Messa la prima Volta in uso la Bolla della Elettione publicata dal Gregorio XV. Fu creato...il Cardinal Maffeo Barberino detto Urbano VIII. Account of the election of Pope Urban VIII in 1623. This was the first Conclave where the Bull by Gregory XV on the elections was put into effect. Title page and 197 pages, numbered ff. 421-518. (Box 85, Folder 17)
  - Conclave di Papa Urbano VIII. Another account of the election of Pope Urban VIII in 1623. 34 pages, numbered ff. 520-536. (Box 85, Folder 18)
- HISTORICAL DOCUMENTS, 13 manuscript items in Italian and Latin. 247
  numbered leaves in all. Small folio. Contemporary vellum (back partly damaged); 3 (of 4) leather ties; uncut. Italy, middle of the 17th century.
  - Index. Loose. 2 leaves. (Box 86, Folder 1)
  - Christina, Queen of Sweeden. Oratione fatta alli Comitii d'Upsala nel mese di Febraio 1654 dalla Regina di Suezia nella Renunza, che fece del Regno di Suezia. The speech made by the Queen at Upsala, previous to her solemn abdication on July 6, 1654. 3 leaves, numbered ff. 1-3. (Box 86, Folder 2)
  - Innocent X, Pope. Bolla assolutoria fatta da Innocentio Decimo al P. Principe Lodovisio di tutti li eccessi...nel tempo del suo Pontificato. Dated Rome, July 16, 1654. Contemporary ms. copy. Niccolo Ludovisi, Prince of Piombino, son-in-law of the Pope's favorite Olimpia Maidalchini, was expelled from Rome in July, 1654, soon after the expulsion of Cardinal Pamfili. (See Pastor XIV/1, p. 37 and note). 2 leaves, numbered ff. 5-6. (Box 86, Folder 3)
  - Guise, Henry, 2nd Duke of. Planetus Guisii Ducis adverso certamine fugienti. In Latin. Poem recording the unfortunate attempt made by the Duke to take over the Realm of Naples on behalf of the King of France. He was captured by the Spaniards near Capua in 1648. 2 leaves, numbered ff. 7-8. (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - Naples, Kingdom of. Ristretto delle Mosse de Francesci per l'Acquisito di Napoli...date nell' Istorie doppo Carlo Primo. Historical survey of the French attempts to govern Naples from Charles I of Anjou (1266) to 1557. In the beginning stanza X, canto 33, by Ariost. 5 leaves, numbered ff. 9-13. (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - (Alexander VII, Pope). Lettera d'un Cortegiano sopra quattro Cardinali Papabili. Copy of a letter discussing the prospects of the Cardinals eligible for the Papacy, restricting the final number to four. N.d. (1655?). 4 leaves, numbered ff. 15-18. (Box 86, Folder 6)
  - Novelli (Lionardo?), Cardinal. Aggionta de G. Cardinali Novelli alla Relatione del Baly di Valenze Ambasciatore di Francia. A refutation (possibly written by Lionardo Novelli, author of a work on papal authority) of a report written by Henri d'Estampes-Valençay, French Ambassador in Rome, 1652- 1653, entitled: Instruttione del Sig. Baili de Valencé...al suo successore (1653, printed 1681). Estampes report describes the inofficial reign of Olimpia Maidalchini, favorite of Pope Innocent X. N.d. (1655). 4 leaves, numbered ff. 19-22. (Box 86, Folder 7)